So in this module we learned a lot about react and some of its core component features.
Bu yzden bu modlde tepki ve ekirdek bileen zelliklerinden bazlar hakknda ok ey reniyoruz.
Since I recorded this course, react 16.3 was released and it offers a couple of nice additions
Bu kursu yeniden kaydettiimden beri 16 dot free serbest brakld ve iinden gemek istediim
which I want to walk you through.
birka gzel eklenti sunuyor.
They fit best into this course module because they affect how we work with components.
Bileenler ile nasl altmz etkiledikleri iin sylem modlne en uygunlar.
Now none of these change is breaking, everything you learned will continue working as you learned it,
Artk bu deiikliklerin hibiri renemeyeceiniz her eyi krmyor ve rendike almaya devam edecek.
it is still correct,
Bu hala doru.
these are simply just some additional features.
Bunlar sadece baz ek zelliklerdir.
Let's start with references,
Referanslarla balayalm.
we use them here in the person component, there we are creating a reference with this ref property on
Onlar burada kullanyoruz ve buradaki kii bileeni, giri elemanndaki bu ref zellii ile
the input element and we're using this ref property to set the focus.
bir referans oluturuyoruz ve oda ayarlamak iin xref zelliini kullanyoruz.
We can see this in effect in our app,
Uygulamamzda bunu etkin olarak grebiliriz.
once I click show persons, we see that the first input here is focused.
Kiileri gster 'i tkladktan sonra, ilk girdinin odaklandn gryoruz.
Now if we're working with refs, react now has an easier way. For this,
imdi yeniden harekete gemeye alyoruz, imdi bunun iin daha kolay bir yol var.
we need to make sure that we're using react version of 16.3 or higher though
16'nn yeniden oynatma srmn kullandmzdan emin olmalyz. 00 bedava ya da daha yksek.
so make sure to update this in your package.json file, save it thereafter and rerun npm install to
Bu nedenle, daha sonra kaydedilen paketlenmi bitiik dosyada bunu gncellediinizden emin olun ve projenizin henz
install these updated package versions in case your project doesn't use that yet.
kullanmad durumda bu gncellenmi paket Persian' yklemek iin NPM yklemesini yeniden altrn.
Once this is done, you can restart your development server
Tamamlandnda, gelitirme sunucunuzu yeniden balatabilirsiniz.
and now let's use that easier way of creating references.
Ve imdi referanslar oluturmann daha kolay bir yolunu kullanalm.
We do that in the constructor by creating a new class property by simply saying this.inputElementRef
Bunu yapcda, bu girdi elemann sadece rnek olarak ya da biz bunu geri aramada bunu yapmadan
for example or just inputElement as we named it before, we do this here in the callback.
nce adlandracamz gibi sadece giri elemann syleyerek yeni bir snf zellii yaratarak yaparz.
Now we simply use react create ref, that's a new method provided by react in the version 16.3
imdi sadece reaktifi yaratmak iin basit bir yntem olan Word ve 16'da tepki olarak kullanyoruz. 00 bedava.
and now we're creating that reference,
Ve imdi l referans oluturuyoruz.
now we just need to inform react which element to connect us to.
imdi sadece bize hangi elementin balanacan yeniden bilgilendirmemiz gerek.
And we do that by going down to our ref property here and instead of using this function callback syntax,
Ve bunu burada reft mlkmze inerek yapyoruz ve bu fonksiyon geri arma szdizimini kullanmak
we simply say this.inputElement.
yerine basite bu girdi elemann sylyoruz.
So we use that property we just created which holds the reference created with react create ref
Bu yzden yeni oluturduumuz bu zellii re-act ref ile yaratlan referans tutan ref kullanyoruz.
and that's almost all,
Ve neredeyse hepsi bu kadar.
now this reference is stored.
imdi bu referans saklanr.
Now there is one difference when we use it, instead of accessing the elements like this,
imdi bu gibi elere erimek yerine onu kullandmzda bir fark var.
we instead have to use access the current property on it because this turns out to be a wrapper component
Bunun yerine zerinde mevcut zellie eriimi kullanmak zorundayz nk bu, bir sarmalayc bileen veya tepki ve
or element provided by react and current gives us access to the underlying dom element.
akm tarafndan salanan eleman olarak ortaya kyor nk bize temeldeki Dom esine eriim salyor.
With that we can save the entire code
Bununla tm kodu kaydedebiliriz.
and now if we reload our app and click show persons, it's still focused but now we're using this easier
Ve imdi uygulamamz yeniden yklersek ve Kiileri gster'i tklarsak hala odaklanrz ancak
reference syntax. React 16.3
imdi bu daha kolay referans szdizimini kullanyoruz.
also introduce a support for forwarded references.
Ayrca ynlendirilmi referanslar iin bir destek tantn.
This means that we actually get a reference from outside of a component, through that component.
Bu, aslnda bir bileenin dndan bu bileenle bir referans aldmz anlamna gelir.
This is especially helpful when working with wrapper classes like the withClass component,
Bu, snf bileeniyle olduu gibi sarmalayc snflaryla alrken zellikle yararldr.
so when working with higher order components I wanted to say. So person for example is wrapped by the with
Bu yzden, yksek mertebeden bileenler ile alrken, rnein, rnein, yksek mertebeden bir
class higher order component and we can actually get access to the person component from the parent
bileenle sarlm olduunu sylemek istiyorum ve aslnda kii bileenine, ana bileenden ya da
components or from persons even though person is wrapped
kii sarl olsa bile yzde cinsinden eriebiliyoruz.
but let's's do this step by step.
Ama bu bir adm adm.
How do we get a reference by default, in the persons.js file,
Kiinin Chaiya sonbaharnda varsaylan olarak nasl bir referans alrz.
let's say we want to get a reference to the last person we're creating.
Diyelim ki yarattmz son kiiye bir referans almak istiyoruz.
So I'll add my last person ref here with react create ref, just as we did with the native html element
Bu yzden Revier'le reistans yeniden oluturmay ve yerel takm l elementinde yaptmz gibi referandum ekleyeceim ve
and now I want to assign the last person we are creating here to this reference.
imdi de bu referansa yeni katlan son kiiyi atamak istiyorum.
The last one simply because we're looping through all persons and if we assign a reference to each of
Sonuncusu basite tm insanlardan geiyor olduumuzdan ve her birine bir referans
them, only the last one will persist because we're constantly overwriting the same reference.
atarsak, yalnzca sonuncusu devam edecektir nk srekli ayn referansn zerine yazyoruz.
We could of course store it in an array but for simplicity, let's simply say we want to store a reference
Elbette bunu bir dizide saklayabilirdik, ancak basitlik iin, burada bir referans saklamak istediimizi
here
syleyelim.
in our this.lastPersonRef property.
Bu son kii ref mlkmzde.
So we assign the ref property to the person and we store that reference to our own component.
Bu yzden ref maln kiiye verdik ve o referans kendi bileenimize saklarz.
Now let's say in our person component here we add a new function,
imdi kii bileenimizde burada yeni bir fonksiyon ekledik.
the focus method which we then could call from outside through the reference
Meffert'in odak noktas, daha sonra Frue'nin referans olarak arayabiliriz.
and here, we actually use our reference in that component to focus it.
Ve ite, biz bu bileene odaklanmak iin referansmz kullanyoruz.
So now what this should theoretically do is for the last person, we want to call focus to put the focus
yleyse imdi teorik olarak ne yapmal, odaklanmak istediimiz son kii iin
on its input rather than the first one.
oda ilk nce deil, girdisine koymaktr.
So let's go back to persons,
O zaman insanlara geri dnelim.
we got our last person reference here.
Son kii referansmz burada aldk.
Now we could go to componentDidMount and use it here and use last person ref current focus.
imdi, bileene gidebiliriz, buraya monte ettik ve burada kullanp son oda geerli oda kullann.
If we do this and we save that, if we reload our app and click on show persons, we actually get an
Bunu yaparsak ve uygulamamz yeniden yklersek ve Pearse'leri gsterebilirsek, aslnda odak noktasnn
error that focus is not a function at persons componentDidMount
kii bileeni miktarnda bir ilev olmadn bir hata hatas alrz.
Now the problem here is that we got the withClass higher order component in between, if I temporarily remove
imdi buradaki problem, o kii bileenini geici olarak kaldrsaydm, snfn daha yksek veya
that in my person component,
bileenli olduunu anladm.
so if I just export person without that wrapping higher order component,
Yani, daha yksek bir sipari bileenini ambalajlamadan sadece kiiyi ihra edersem.
if I do that and I reload
Eer bunu yaparsam ve yeniden yklerim.
and now I click show person, now it actually works fine and we're focusing the last input because we're
Ve imdi talk show kiisi u anda gerekten iyi alyor ve biz son girdiye
now calling the focus method in the person component
odaklanyoruz nk artk biz kii bileenindeki odaklama yntemini aryoruz.
for the last person in our array of persons, we do that with a reference to our own component,
Kiiler dizimizdeki son kii iin bunu kendi bileenimize referansla yapyoruz.
this works fine.
Bu iyi alyor.
However the problem is we do have that wrapper higher order component and this is actually not forward
Ancak sorun u ki, bu sarmalayc yksek mertebeden bir bileen var ve bu aslnda
the outer reference, this is just how react works. The ref property is a special property and it's not forwarded
zorlanmad d referans nasl yeniden re-act alr ref zellikleri zel bir zellik ve
even though in withClass, we do distribute all our props on the wrap component.
snf iin bile tm props zerinde datmak ramen dolandrclk iin deil sarma bileeni.
Now we can fix this issue in our higher order component, for the wrapped component
imdi bu sorunu sarlm bileen iin yksek sipari bileenimizde dzeltebiliriz.
we have to forward the reference, so we have to set the ref attribute here because this wrapped component
Referans iletmek zorundayz, bu nedenle ref zniteliini burada ayarlamamz gerekiyor nk bu
will be our Person component in the end.
sarl bileen bizim Kii bileenimiz olacak.
For this however we need to get that reference from outside, we want to forward it
Ancak bunun iin dardan aktarmak istediimiz referans almamz gerekiyor.
so we want to get that reference, we're assigning in a persons component in our case. To do this, we
Dolaysyla bu referans almak iin bir kiinin bir bileeninde bir saat
need to get access to these forwarded reference and we can simply assume that on our prop, we have
atarz, bunu yapmak iin bu referanslara erimemiz gerekir ve mlkmzde 4
let's say a forwarded ref,
veya ilave bir ref ekleyelim.
this name is totally up to you though.
Bu isim tamamen size kalm.
And this should be this.props, of course.
Ve bu prop elbette olmal.
Now we're accessing this,
imdi buna eriiyoruz.
however we won't have this property on our props.
Bununla birlikte, bu mlkmze sahip olmayacaz.
To ensure that we got it,
S Ve aldmzdan eminim.
we simply go to our persons component where we are passing ref and instead of passing ref, we now pass
Biz sadece ref getiimiz ve ref getiimizde ref olarak
forwarded ref.
getiimiz kiiler bileenimize gideriz.
Now you could think this is it,
imdi bunun olduunu dnebilirsin.
so if we save this and we reload and click show persons, it does indeed work.
Yani eer bunu korursak ve yeniden ykleyip Kiileri gster'i tklarsanz gerekten alr.
It is however inconvenient that we have to manually set forwarded ref here in the persons component, would
Ancak, el ile ileriye doru ve ref dzeltmemiz gerekmedii iin elverili bir durumdur ve eer ref'yi
be nice if we could still use ref. And then we go to our withClass higher order component and in there
kullanmaya devam edersek, bileen bileenimiz daha iyi olur ve daha sonra snf yksek sipari bileeniyle birlikte gideriz ve
we can use the new forward ref API react 16.3 introduced. Instead of returning the class
burada yeni ileriye doru geri bildirim API'sine tepki verebiliriz. Snf iade etmek yerine  takm ya da  tantrd.
here, we can first of all store it in a component withClass
Burada her eyden nce snfla birlikte bir bileende saklayabiliriz.
for example in a constant excuse me and we want to return that,
Mesela srekli bir mazeretle ve bunu geri vermek istiyoruz.
however what we'll actually return here is we'll return a call to react forward ref like this and
Ancak aslnda bir yl geri dnecek olan ey, Ward gazabnn dis gibi tepki vermesi iin bir ar
this in turn receives an argument which is a function that gets the props and the reference argument
dndrecektir. Ve bu da, sahne ve referans argmann alan bir ilev olan
and will then here return withClass, distribute our props into it and also set that forwarded
bir argman alr ve sonra snf datmyla geri dnn ona bir sahne olduunu duyacaktr. ve ayn zamanda drdn,
ref equal to the ref we're receiving.
aldmz ref'e eit ref eklendiini de syledi.
Now his entire logic is contained in our higher order component.
imdi tm mant yksek mertebeden bileenimizde yer alyor.
If I saved this and I reload and click show persons it still works as before and it's not an issue for
Eer onu kurtardysam ve yeniden ykleyip Kiileri gster'i tklatrsanz daha nce olduu gibi alr ve bir ref ayarlanmadan yksek
components where we used that higher order component without setting a ref
sipari bileeninde kullandmz bileenler iin bir sorun deildir.
by the way but we don't have to set the forwarded ref property in our other components, it's all
Bu arada, ortalama bileenimizdeki ref zelliini ne koymak zorunda deiliz, bunlarn hepsi,
included in that withClass component which of course is way more convenient than having to manually
snf ismiyle birlikte yer alyor. Elbette, tm isimleri manuel olarak ayarlamaktan
adjust all the names.
daha uygun.
So this is how we can work with refs, how we can simply use that easier syntax with just create ref and
Dolaysyla, bu kadar basit bir szdizimini sadece ref oluturun ve ileriye dnk tm referanslar nasl yapabileceimizi basite nasl
how we can also forward references.
kullanabileceimiz ile ilgili olarak alabiliriz.
This is something you might not need that often but if you need it, it's really useful.
Bu, sk sk ihtiya duyamayacanz bir eydir, ancak ihtiyacnz varsa gerekten faydaldr.